A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Program, Office Files of Richard C. Robarts FA701
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Program, Office Files of Richard C. Robarts
1966-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Robarts, Richard C.
FA701
2.2 Cubic Feet
The Middle East and Africa (MEA) Files from the Office of Richard C. Robarts were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in July 1982. The MEA Files include both the files which Robarts created and maintained (Series III) and those files that were created by MEA staff, including Robarts' successors Ann Lesch, Sidney Jones and Judy Barsalou, and maintained in Robarts' office (Series I and II). Arrangement within the series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by the MEA Office. In 1995, the Archives received files from the office of Steven M. Riskin. Riskin was as assistant program officer and program officer in MEA, January 1984-June 1992 and subsequently, a Foundation consultant. These files proved to be MEA files that had remained in Robarts' office subsequent to the transfer of Robarts' files in 1982. They have been accessioned as ACC95/1 and now constitute Series IV.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been transferred to the Archives' collections of unpublished staff and consultant reports and grant-related publications. Their locations have been noted on cross-reference sheets within the files. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been discarded.
Biographical / Historical
Richard C. Robarts was a member of the Ford Foundation staff from March 1963 until September 1982. During this period, he held the following positions:
• September 1980, Program Officer, MEA, N.Y., International Division • July 1977, Deputy Representative, MEA, Cairo, International Division • July 1973, Program Officer, MEA, N.Y., International Division • July 1972, FF Study Leave, Paris • October 1966, Asst. to the Rep., MEA, Lebanon, International Division • October 1964, Asst. to the Rep., N.E. MEA, Lebanon, Overseas Development • March 1963, Asst. to the Dir., N.Y., Administration
Richard Robarts was born July 22, 1932. He received his Bachelor of Arts (B.A.) degree in 1955 from Bowdoin College, and was elected Phi Beta Kappa. In 1956, Robarts was awarded the Master of Arts in Teaching degree from Yale University. In 1962, he received the Master in International Affairs degree from Columbia University.
Prior to his tenure at the Ford Foundation Mr. Robarts held the following positions:
• 1962-63, American Telephone and Telegraph, Public Relations Asst. • 1958-60, Press Herald, Portland, ME, Reporter
After his departure from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Robarts became the Executive Director of the Near East Foundation, New York, New York.
Scope and Contents
The MEA Files from the Office of Richard C. Robarts consist of four linear feet (10 archives boxes) of correspondence, inter-office memoranda and cables. The MEA files arranged and described 1984-1986, document the administration of the MEA office between 1966 and 1974. Records accessioned in 1995 and organized as Series IV, document various activities from 1966 to 1982.
Arrangement
The MEA Files from the Office of Richard C. Robarts are arranged in four series:
I. MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1967 - 1974
II. MEA Field Office Budget Correspondence, 1969 - 1974
III. Richard C. Robarts Office Correspondence, 1966 (1973 - 1974)
IV. MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1966 - 1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1967 - 1974; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I deals with four field offices: Beirut, Cairo, Tunis and Israel.
  Arrangement
  Series I, MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1967 - 1974, is divided by Field Office: Beirut, Cairo, Tunis, and Israel. For each field office the files are arranged in reverse chronological order. Within each folder the items are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Beirut, 1972 - 1973; 1
    - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13-22)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cairo, 1972 - 1974; 2
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
    - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 28-36)
    - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37-42)
    - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 43-48)
    - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 49-57)
  - Tunis, 1967 - 1974; 3
    - 1974 (Box 5, Folder 58-69)
    - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 70-81)
    - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 82-88)
    - 1971 (Box 5, Folder 89-90)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - 1968 (Box 6, Folder 93-104)
    - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 105-106)
  - Israel, 1970 - 1973; 4
    - 1973 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - 1972 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - 1970 (Box 6, Folder 110)
- MEA Field Office Budget Correspondence, 1969 - 1974; II
  Series II deals with two field offices: Tunis (1969 - 1973) and Beirut (1970 - 1974). This series contains correspondence concerning program management costs, manpower projections, and budget reports. Both this series and Series I include correspondence from Ford Foundation's field office staff: Piero Bronzi, Robert Edwards, Wesley S. Edwards, Melvin Fox, Wayne Fredericks, Wilbert J. Le Melle, Courtney A. Nelson, Thomas F. Olson, Thomas D. Scott, and Betty Skolnick.
  Series II, MEA Field Office Budget Correspondence, 1969 - 1974, contains budget-related correspondence from Tunis and Beirut. The files are divided by field office and are arranged in reverse chronological order. Within each folder the items are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Tunis, 1969 - 1973; 1
    - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - 1971 (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - 1970 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - 1969 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Beirut, 1970 - 1974; 2
    - 1974 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - 1971 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - 1970 (Box 7, Folder 120)
- Richard C. Robarts Office Correspondence, 1966 (1973 - 1974), III
  Series III, Richard C. Robarts Office Correspondence, 1966 (1973 - 1974), contains Robarts' outgoing correspondence, memoranda and cables as well as a very small amount of incoming correspondence. The files are arranged in reverse chronological order. Within each folder the items are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Series III is the chronological file of Robarts' out-going letters and memoranda. This series documents Robart's administrative responsibilities.
  - 1974 (Box 7, Folder 121-130)
  - 1974 (Box 8, Folder 130-132)
  - 1973 (Box 8, Folder 133-138)
  - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 139)
- MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1966 - 1982; IV
  Series IV (ACC95/1) contains Beirut quarterly forecast files, 1966-1967; correspondence concerning the Foundation's departure from Beirut, 1975-1977, including information on termination of staff; correspondence pertaining to the Foundation's departure from Saudi Arabia, 1976-1978; correspondence to/from Robarts and Foundation staff and others concerning the Foundation's interest in the Persian Gulf States, especially Kuwait and Bahrain, 1975-1976; material regarding the Foundation's response to the Arab boycott of Israel, 1975-1977; memoranda to/from Courtney Nelson, 1972-1976; memoranda and trip reports from Cynthia Myntti, 1981-1982; and correspondence from the Cairo Field Office regarding the human rights/legal aid consultancy of George Cooper, 1981-1982.
  Series IV, MEA Field Office Correspondence, 1966 - 1982, has not been arranged.
  - Beirut quarterly forecasts, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Beirut quarterly forecasts, 1967 January - April (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Beirut quarterly forecasts, 1967 October - 1968 February (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - "Beirut Emergency File" (confidential), 1975 - 1977 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - "Beirut Retrenchment File", 1975 November - 1976 June (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - "Beirut Retrenchment File", 1976 July - 1977 May (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Saudi Arabia, 1976 - 1978 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Gulf Coast, Kuwait, Bahrain, 1975 - 1976 (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Arab Boycott of Israel, 1975 - 1977 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Arab Boycott of Israel, 1975 - 1977 (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Arab Boycott of Israel (clippings), 1975 - 1977 (Box 10, Folder 150)
  - Memoranda to/from Courtney Nelson, 1972 - 1974 (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Memoranda to/from Courtney Nelson, 1975 - 1976 (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Memoranda and trip reports from Cynthia Myntti, 1981 - 1982 (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Human rights/legal aid consultancy (George Cooper), 1981 - 1982 (Box 10, Folder 154)